<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea at large, for John Lilburn gentleman, now a prisoner in Newgate. Penned for his use and benefit, by a faithful and true well-wisher to the fundamental laws, liberties, and freedoms of the antient free people of England; and exposed to publick view, and the censure of the unbyassed and learned men in the laws of England, Aug. 6. 1653.</title>
            <author>Faithful and true well-wisher to the fundamental laws, liberties, and freedoms of the antient free people of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E710_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207176</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866245</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866245</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 109:E710[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea at large, for John Lilburn gentleman, now a prisoner in Newgate. Penned for his use and benefit, by a faithful and true well-wisher to the fundamental laws, liberties, and freedoms of the antient free people of England; and exposed to publick view, and the censure of the unbyassed and learned men in the laws of England, Aug. 6. 1653.</title>
                  <author>Faithful and true well-wisher to the fundamental laws, liberties, and freedoms of the antient free people of England.</author>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated on last page: 'July 13. 1653. John Lilburn Gentleman'.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PLEA at large, For <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN</hi> Gentleman, now a priſoner in NEWGATE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Penned for his uſe and benefit, by a faithful and true well-wiſher to the Fundamental Laws, Liberties, and Freedoms of the antient free people of <hi>England;</hi> and expoſed to publick view, and the cenſure of the unbyaſſed and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in the Laws of <hi>England, Aug.</hi> 6. 1653.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOhn Lilburn</hi> Gent. now priſoner at the Bar ſaith, That he having heard the Charge contained in the Indictment now read unto him at the Bar; for Plea thereunto he ſaith, That it appeareth by the Act of Parliament of <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1651. That upon the 15 of <hi>January</hi> 1651 a judgement was given in Parliament againſt one Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> in the Act named, for high Crimes and Miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours by him committed; as by the ſame appears, for which the Fines and other pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments were promulgated againſt him, mentioned in the ſaid Act. But the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the Bar ſaith, That the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> in the ſaid Act named, and he the now priſoner at the Bar, be not one and the ſelf ſame perſon, for that he the now priſoner at the Bar is a free-born Engliſh Gentleman, and never was legally Charged, Indicted, and convicted, either by the Parliament or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Court of Judicature, being a Court of Record, in the Engliſh Nation, or Commonwealth. And he ſaith, that the Parliament being diſſolved, and by the Law of Parliament in all dubious caſes, there being no other way to render the ſenſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118510:2"/>
and meaning of the Parliament, being a body politick, but by Vote of Parliament he ſaith it is now impoſſible; if the Speaker himſelf, and all the individual mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſaid Parliament ſhould upon their oaths be produced at the Bar; yet it is impoſſible by all their oaths, in Law to prove the <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the Bar, to be that Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> that the ſaid Parliament in the ſaid Act of baniſhment meant, becauſe by the Law of Parliament there is no other way in all dubious caſes to render the ſenſe of Parliament, but by the ſolemn Vote of the Parliament fitting as a Parliament, and paſſing it thereupon as a body politick.</p>
            <p>And the priſoner at the Bar further ſaith, Neither was there any Judgement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Parliament againſt him the now priſoner at the Bar, for high Crimes and Miſdemeanours mentioned in the ſaid Act, upon the ſaid fifteenth of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. Votes and Reſolves being not in the leaſt any Judgements in Law, but at moſt only prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to more ſerious, ſolemn, and judicious things that are to follow them; for what at moſt are they, or can they in Law be called or ſtiled? can they in any ſenſe be ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Judgements? No, its impoſſible: becauſe they are no ſuch things in themſelves; for I reſolve to go to ſuch a place, on ſuch a day; and it may be within an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I reſolve to the contrary; is this a Judgement? No: <hi>Vantrump</hi> the Dutch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral reſolved at the laſt Sea-fight, or the laſt ſea-fight before that, to beat the Engliſh Navy, but when he came throughly to try it, he was not able to do it: was therefore his reſolve a Judgement, or the act of beating the Engliſh Fleet ever the more done becauſe he reſolved it? No: and therefore <hi>John Lilburn</hi> Gent. the now priſoner at the Bar ſaith again, That a Reſolve at moſt is but a preparative to the doing or perfecting of a more ſolemn act: as for inſtance, a vicious man reſolves to lye with his neighbours wife, is that an act therefore ever the more done, becauſe he reſolves it? No: for it may be for all his reſolve he will never be able to accompliſh it, or do the act whiles he breaths. Again, the Lord himſelf in <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. reſolved to deſtroy and root out the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for making them a golden Calf, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping it, when <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the Mountain, yet that reſolve never came to a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor never was executed. Again, <hi>David</hi> in the ſecond of <hi>Samuel</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth, reſolved to build God a houſe, yet God would not let it be done by him (becauſe he was a man of blood) but it was done by his ſon <hi>Solomon:</hi> was that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve therefore a Judgement; or ever the more to be eſteemed ſo, becauſe <hi>David</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved it? no, not in the leaſt.</p>
            <p>And the priſoner at the Bar further ſaith, that it is in Law, Equity or Reaſon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that a Judgement in any legal Court of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be paſt againſt a free-born Engliſhman, and that man dayly forth coming, and never to hear, read, nor ſee any of the proceedings anteceding the ſaid Judgement: and never ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any legal proceſſes to any legal proceedings; nor called to any legal Bar what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and demanded (according to Law) what he could ſay for himſelf, why Judgement ſhould not be paſt againſt him. Neither did the priſoner <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now at the Bar, ever in all his life time, by kneeling at the Bar of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> lately ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> ever acknowledge that the ſaid Parliament in Law ever had in all their life times, any the leaſt juriſdiction in the world, to ſentence him in any kinde, or to fine, impriſon or baniſh him, or any other free-born Engliſhman of <hi>England,</hi> though never ſo mean (that are none of their members or immediate officers) for any crimes whatſoever; which is not by Law in the leaſt within their power, upon any pretence whatſoever: As <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> the priſoner at the Bar hath fully and undenyably proved by Law in his Plea (upon the Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi>) before the late Judges of the Kings Bench; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118510:2"/>
Judge <hi>Bacon</hi> and Judge <hi>Rolls,</hi> upon the eighth of <hi>May,</hi> 1648. as in that printed Law-Argument Entituled <hi>The Laws funeral,</hi> it is fully to be read, in <hi>pag.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11. All crimes whatſoever being for him, onely and ſolely to be heard, determined, and judged at the Common Law and nowhere elſe, all treaſons being only to be tryed at the Common law, by a Jury of twelve legal men of the neighbourhood, as expreſly appeareth by the Statute of 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>chap.</hi> 10. and the 1 of <hi>May chap.</hi> 1. &amp; 2 of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chap.</hi> 10. and ſo are all miſdemeanours or breaches of peace, though it be in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting, beating, or wounding (which is much more then by papers diſgracing) any Parliamentman, for thats expreſly to be tryed by the Kings (or now as it is called upper) bench, as clearly appears by the fifth of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>chap.</hi> 6. <hi>and the</hi> 11. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>cha.</hi> 11. Yea although a Sheriff by law is to pay a hundred pound to the King, or now as they are called, To the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and to ſuffer a yeers impriſonment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without Baile or Mainepriſe, for every falſe return of a Knight of the ſhire that he makes, yet by law, the Houſe of Commons in former time, were not in the leaſt to be Judges in this very buſineſs, ſo immediately concerning themſelves; but it ſhall be examined and tryed before the Juſtices of Aſſizes in the Seſſions of the Aſſize, as appeareth by the 8. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>chap.</hi> 7. <hi>and</hi> 23. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>chap.</hi> 15. Yea the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are not to puniſh thoſe that will not pay them their wages for their ſervice done in Parliament, but the refuſers are to be puniſhed by the legal adminiſters of the law in the ordinary of Courts of Juſtice, as appears by the 23. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>chap.</hi> 11. Yea the law of <hi>England,</hi> which is right reaſon, or as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> ſtiles it (in his ſecond part Inſtitutes, <hi>folio</hi> 179.) the abſolute perfection of reaſon; and which, as he ſaith, is the ſureſt ſanctuary that a man can take, and the ſtrongeſt fortreſs to protect the weakeſt of all; and therefore it is called the beſt birthright the Subjects hath, for thereby his goods, lands, wife, children, his body, life, honour, and eſtimation are protected from injury and wrong; for (ſaith he) to every one of us, there comes a greater inheritance by the law then by our parents, it being the Judges guide in all cauſes that come before them, in the wayes of right Juſtice, which never yet miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided any man that certainly knew them, and truly followed them, 2 <hi>part.</hi> of the Lords <hi>Cooks</hi> Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 56, 63, 97, 526. and the 4. <hi>part folio</hi> 41. yea and the law-book of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>folio</hi> 36. with the arguments in the Law in the Court of Kings Bench, upon the Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> in the caſes of Sir <hi>John Eliot,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Daniel,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 11. in <hi>Michaelmas</hi>-terme, in the third of the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> calls the good old fundamental Laws of <hi>England,</hi> the great inheritance of every ſubject, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of inheritances; without the injoyments of which inheritance, we have no inheritance at all. And therefore the ſaid Oracle of the Law of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> doth bitterly cry out of the unexpreſſible miſchief that accrues to the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the people of <hi>England,</hi> when any fundamental maximes of their good old fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws are invaded or incroached upon, either by Parliament, or any other power whatſoever, as appears in his 2 <hi>part</hi> Inſtitutes <hi>folio</hi> 29, 46, 48, 51 74, 103, 104, 179, 210, 249, 529, 533, 534, 540. and 3. part <hi>fol.</hi> 208. &amp; 4. part <hi>fol.</hi> 41, 196, 197 198. and the preface to the 4. part of the Lord <hi>Cookes</hi> Reports, where he ſaith the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> conſiſt of three parts, the Common Laws, Cuſtomes, and Acts of Parliament; for any fundamental point of the ancient Common Laws and cuſtoms of the Realm it is a maxime in policy, and a tryal by experience, that the alteration of any of them is more dangerous: for that which hath been refined and perfected by all the wiſeſt men in former ſucceſſion of ages, and proved and approved by continual experience to be good and profitable for the Commonwealth, cannot without great hazard
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118510:3"/>
and danger to be altered or changed: ſee alſo that old Law-book, called <hi>The myrror of Juſtice,</hi> page 239.</p>
            <p>And which law, as the author of the ancient and excellent law book, called <hi>the Doctor and Student,</hi> chap. 4.8. is grounded upon ſix foundation, or baſis, <hi>viz.</hi> the law of reaſon. Secondly, the Law of God. 3. Upon divers general cuſtomes of common utility. 4. On divers principals that be called maximes. 5. On divers particular cuſtomes. 6. On divers Statutes made by the Kings and the Common-councel of the Nation; all which do abhor arbitra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ineſs in the law-proceedings, eſpecially in criminal caſes; and eſpecially it abhors the arbitrary uncertain way of proceedings in Parliaments, the rules of which certainly no man in heaven or earth knoweth (the vileneſs, wickedneſs, and miſcheviouſneſs of which, is ſufficiently demonſtrated in the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> late printed caſe.) And ſaith that worthieſt of Engliſh Lawyers Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> in the Proeme to the third part of his Inſtitutes, It is a miſerable ſervitude or ſlavery, where the law is uncertaine or unknown; and therefore it is that the twenty ninth Chapter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the Petition of Right, and the Act that aboliſhed the Star-Chamber, expreſly ſaith, <hi>That no freeman of</hi> England <hi>ſhall be taken or impriſoned, or diſſeized of his freehold, or liberties, or free cuſtomes, or be outlawed, or be exiled, but by lawful judgement (of a Jury of twelve ſworn men) of his equals (of the ſame neighbourhood) according to the law of the Land. And that none ſhall be taken (for any crime whatſoever, by any perſon or Court whatſoever) unleſs it be by Indictment or Preſentment of good and lawful people of the ſame neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, where ſuch Deeds be done, in due manner, or by Proceſs made by Writ original at the Common Law; and that none be put out of his franchiſe or freehold, unleſs he be duly brought in to anſwer, and adjudged of the ſame according to the courſe of the law; and if any thing be done (by any perſons, or courts whatſoever) againſt the tenour of the ſame, it ſhall be void in law, and holden for error:</hi> which two laſt Statutes of the Petition of Right, and the Act that abol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſheth the Star-chamber, doth expreſly and nominally ratifie and confirme the Statute of the 42. of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, which according to the peoples true fundamental law of <hi>England,</hi> makes void and null all Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Ordinances, Orders, Judgements, and Decrees whatſoever, made by any power whatſoever, that are contrary unto, or in diminution of the free people of <hi>Englands</hi> foreſaid liberties and freedoms of due Proceſs of Law. And the Petition of Right expreſly ſaith, <hi>No man whatſoever ſhall be any wayes puniſhed (eſpecially in cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal caſes) but according to the laws and Statutes already eſtabliſhed in the land.</hi> And thoſe alſo by the ſaid Petition of Right, and the Statute that aboliſhed the Star-chamber, are preciſely declared to be according to our good old native fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal rights and liberties, or elſe they are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> null and void in law; this very thing (or the ſecuring thereof) alone, being the principal and chief declared cauſe of all the late Parliaments, and preſent armies bloodſhed and wars with the late King and his ſon, and without the inviolable preſervation of theſe our funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental laws and liberties, it is impoſſible that any in the Army, from the higheſt to the loweſt, in the leaſt can acquit themſelves of being juſtly eſteemed, both before God and juſt men, real and wilful murderers of all thoſe perſons that they have ſtaine in the late civil wars; and if ſo, wo unto them when God makes inquiſition for innocent blood.</p>
            <p>Neither indeed is he the now priſoner at the Bar guilty of any ſuch high crimes and miſdemeanors as is expreſſed in the ſaid Act; neither ever was he the now priſoner at the Bar in the leaſt duely and legally baniſhed and fined by the ſaid Act; nor yet is a Felon, nor guilty of felony in no manner of reſpect whatſoever, as by the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118510:3"/>
now read unto him is ſuppoſed: neither can he rationally imagine that by the Parliament that is mentioned in the ſaid Act of the 30 of <hi>January</hi> 1651. for ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing one Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> is in the leaſt meant the late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (eſpecially, becauſe it is not ſo therein expreſt) who had taken many Oaths, and paſt abundance of Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and particularly that of the 9 of <hi>February</hi> 1648. inviolably to maintain the Fundamental Laws of the Land, in reference to the Peoples lives, liberties, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, with all things incident, appertaining, and belonging thereunto: But that rather it was ſome ignorant ſottiſh French Parliament ſitting at <hi>Paris</hi> or elſewhere in <hi>France,</hi> that underſtand nothing of the Laws, Liberties, and Freedoms of <hi>England;</hi> or that it was the malignant Cavalier Parliament lately ſitting at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the Kings Quarters there, poſt-dating their Act, and thereby endeavouring by the ſaid Act to create ſuch a preſident as in the conſequence of it would deſtroy all the Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Properties of the free-born people of <hi>England,</hi> and thereby abſolutely ſet up the Kings will and prerogative above Law; the bare endeavouring of which, in the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> hath been long ſince adjudged high treaſon. Or in the next place, it the authors of the ſaid monſtrous and illegal Act of Baniſhment be neither the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> nor the Cavalier Parliament of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Then of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the third place, it cannot in charity and reaſon but be judged that the ſaid Act of Baniſhment was drawn up by Mr. <hi>Scobel</hi> the Parliaments Clerk, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> their Chayr-man, and Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> their Attorney and Poſt-maſter-general, when they were all riding poſt, and ſo jumbled or ſhaken with faſt riding, that it was impoſſible for them to hold their pens to write right and true: and when they had framed it, then by ſome cunning artifice or inchantment of theirs, they preferred it to the ſaid Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, who in charity and common reaſon muſt needs be judged to paſs it when they were three quarters aſleep, againſt ſome ſilly natural fool called Lieutenant-Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> that could not be imagined ever in his life to have read any thing of Law or Reaſon, it being impoſſible (in the leaſt in reaſon to be conceived) that the late Supreme Authority, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> being onely by their own Declarations, but truſted to provide for the peoples weal, but not in the leaſt for their wo, would ever in their right wits, or not being three quarters aſleep, paſs ſuch an Act of Parliament againſt <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the Bar (who hath much read the Law, and very well underſtands the Fundamental Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and hath hazardouſly adventured his life a thouſand cimes, for the inviolable preſerving of them) becauſe ſuch an Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament as the foreſaid Act of Parliament, is in the firſt place an Act of Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt common right, common equity, and common reaſon; and therefore is void and null in Law, and ought not to be executed, as appears by theſe following autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 part of Dr. <hi>Bonham</hi>'s Caſe, <hi>fol.</hi> 118. and the 8 of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 3, 30, 33. <hi>F. Ceſſavit.</hi> 32 &amp; 27 <hi>H. G. Annuity</hi> 41. and 1 <hi>Eliz. Dyer,</hi> 113. and 1 part <hi>Cook</hi>'s Inſtitutes, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. Chap. 11. Sect. 209. <hi>fol.</hi> 140. and 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.12. and 12 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.18. and 1 <hi>H.</hi> 7.12, 13. and <hi>Plowd.</hi> Com. <hi>fol.</hi> 369. and Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> learned works in the Law, printed for <hi>J. Giles,</hi> 1648. but particularly, by his Diſcourſe of Long Parliaments, p. 139, 140. and ſee alſo Mr. <hi>W. Prynne</hi>'s notable book of the 16 of <hi>June</hi> 1649. called, <hi>A Legal Vindication of the Liberties of</hi> England <hi>againſt illegal Taxes,</hi> p. 11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſee a book intituled <hi>The Legal Fundamental Liberties of</hi> England <hi>revived, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and vindicated,</hi> printed and reprinted in the yeer 1649 page 54, 55, 56, 57. yea an Act of Parliament that a man ſhall be judge in his own caſe, is a void Act in law, as appears in <hi>Hubberts</hi> Caſe, <hi>fol.</hi> 120. and by the 8 part of <hi>Cook</hi>'s Reports, in Dr. <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118510:4"/>
Caſe, and by the preſent Armies own Book of Declarations, p. 35, 52, 54, 59, 60, 61, 63, 132, 141, 142, 143, 144. yea, ſaith that learned Oracle of the Law of <hi>England</hi> Sir <hi>Edw. Cook,</hi> in the 4 part of his Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 330. <hi>Where Reaſon ceaſeth, there the Law ceaſeth: for, ſeeing Reaſon is the very life and ſpirit of the Law it ſelf, the Law-giver is not to be eſteemed, to reſpect that which hath no reaſon, although the generality of the words, at the firſt ſight, or after the letter, ſeem otherwiſe.</hi> And ſaith the ſaid learned Author, in his firſt part Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 140. <hi>All Cuſtoms and Preſcriptions, Acts of Parliament, Laws and Judgements, that be againſt Reaſon, are void and null in themſelves.</hi> And ſaith the Armies Sollicitor-General, <hi>John Cook,</hi> in the late <hi>Kings Caſe ſtated,</hi> p. 23. <hi>That by the law of England, any Act or Agreement againſt the Laws of God and Nature, is a meer nullity: for as a man hath no hand in making the Laws of God and Nature, no more hath he power to marre or alter them.</hi> And he cites the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi>'s adjudged Caſe for a proof. And in page 20 he alſo ſaith, that all the Judges in <hi>England</hi> cannot make one Caſe to be Law that is not Reaſon, no more then they can prove an hair to be white that is black: which if they ſhould ſo declare or adjudge, it is a meer nullity: <hi>for Law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>must be Reaſon adjudged.</hi> And therefore ſaith he, page 8. <hi>That man or men that rules by luſt, and not by law, is or are creatures that were never of Gods making, nor of Gods approbation, but his permiſſion: and though ſuch men be ſaid to be gods on earth, 'tis in no other ſenſe then the devil is called the god of this world.</hi> And excellent to this very purpoſe is that ancient Law-book called <hi>The Doctor and Student,</hi> who in his ſecond Chapter, pag. 4. expreſly ſayth, <hi>Againſt the law of Nature</hi> (which he calls the Law of Reaſon) <hi>Preſcription, Statute, or Cuſtoms may not prevail: and if any be brought in againſt it, they be no Preſcriptions, Statutes, nor Cuſtoms, but things void, and againſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> And what this law of Nature or Reaſon is, he excellently ſheweth in the latter end of the fourth page, and the beginning of the fifth: and therefore in pag. 7. he expreſty ſaith, <hi>That to every good Law is required theſe properties,</hi> viz. <hi>That it be honeſt, right wiſe, poſſible in it ſelf, and after the cuſtom of the Country; convenient for the place and time, neceſſary, profitable, and alſo manifeſt that it be not captious by any dark ſentence, nor mixt with any private wealth, but all made for the common good: for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>every mans law muſt be conſonant to the Law of God, otherwiſe they are not righteous nor obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi> All which Judgements or Caſes in Law, in the equitable and rational part of them, are fully confirmed by that commonly reputed able Lawyer Serjeant <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> late Lord Preſident of the high Court of Juſtice againſt King <hi>Charles;</hi> who in his large Speech to him, and againſt him, printed in the ſecond Edition of his Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and ſold by <hi>Peter Cole, Francis Tyton,</hi> and <hi>John Playford,</hi> 1650. from p. 52. to 70. And amongſt other paſſages in p. 55. he hath this: <hi>That the end of having Kings or any other Governours, it is for the enjoying of juſtice; that is the end. Now Sir,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if ſo be the King will go contrary to that end, or any other Governour will go contrary to the end of his Government, he muſt underſtand that he is but an Officer in truſt, and he or they ought to diſcharge that truſt, and they are to take order for the animadverſion and puniſhment of ſuch an offending Governour.</hi> And in p. 53. he tells the King, <hi>That as the Law is his ſuperiour, ſo alſo</hi> he tells him <hi>there is ſomething that is ſuperiour to the Law, and that is indeed the parent or author of the Law, and that is the people of</hi> England: <hi>for Sir, as they are thoſe that at the firſt (as other Countries have done) did chuſe to themſelves this form of Government, even for Juſtice ſake, that juſtice might be administred, that peace might be preſerved: ſo that Sir</hi> (ſaith he to the King) <hi>the people gave Laws to Governours, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which they ſhould govern: and if thoſe Laws ſhould have proved inconvenient or prejudicial to the Publike, the People had a power in them, and reſerved to themſelves, to alter them as they ſhall ſee cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118510:4"/>Secondly, ſuch an Act of Parliament as the aforeſaid Act of Baniſhment, is not onely againſt common right, common equity, and common reaſon; but it is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deſtructive to the very ends of the peoples Truſt conferred upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo the higheſt of treaſons that can be committed. And that it is deſtructive to the ends of the peoples Truſt, clearly appears by the Statutes of 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. cap. 14 and 16 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.10. which expreſly ſaith, that <hi>a Parliament at least ſhall be holden once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeer;</hi> and that <hi>for the maintenance of the peoples Laws and Liberties, and the redreſs of divers miſchiefs and grievances that daily happen.</hi> And ſutable to theſe things are the ends contained in the Writs that ſummon them, and the intentions of thoſe that chuſe the Members and ſend them. And ſutable to this, is the end of the Parliaments ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as the preſent General and his Army in many of their remarkable Declarations have fully declared, againſt the late 11 Members and their accomplices, yea and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the late Parliament to raze out of their books and Records many wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt things, as they judged them to be, after the Parliament had ſolemnly paſt them, as Votes, Orders, Judgements, and Acts, yea and endeavoured very earneſtly to hang divers of thoſe as Traytors that had executed them, as particularly Alderman <hi>Adams,</hi> Alderman <hi>Langham,</hi> Alderman <hi>Bunce,</hi> with the Lord Maior Sir <hi>John Gayre,</hi> and divers others. But the greateſt grievances and miſchiefs in the world are by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid miſchievous and unjuſt Baniſhing Act eſtabliſhed, ratified, and confirmed: for by it a man is condemned to loſe his liberty and eſtate, and the comforts of this life, and that without any the leaſt crime committed, or accuſation exhibited, or legal Proceſſes iſſued out, to ſummon the party to make any defence in the world, or ever calling or permitting him to ſpeak one word for himſelf; which is an Act or procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt the light and law of Nature, Reaſon, the Law of God, againſt the law of Honour, Conſcience, and common Honeſty; yea, a dealing worſe with the party, then ever the cruel Jews did with Chriſt, or then the bloody butchers Biſhop <hi>Gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> and <hi>Bonner</hi> did with the roſted Martyrs in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, who always ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to have due proceſſes of Law, and to know and ſee their accuſers, and to have free liberty to ſpeak for themſelves; and never condemned them, but for tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing a known and declared law in being. Yea, alſo dealing worſe with the party, then ever the bloody Gunpowder-Traytors were dealt with by King <hi>James,</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways allowed them fair tryals in law, from the beginning to the end, at the Bar of Juſtice for their lives. Yea, it is a worſe dealing with the party, then ever the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament themſelves dealt with the bloodieſt and moſt maſſacring Traytors that ever were in Arms againſt them to cut their throats. Yea, the forementioned practice of the foreſaid moſt illegal and unrighteous Act of Baniſhment, is an Act and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the higheſt ſubverſion of the Fundamental Law and Liberty of <hi>England</hi> that can be invented or imagined; and by conſequence, if it may without the higheſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or ſoloeciſm in Law be ſuppoſed, that his Excellencie the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> Major-Gen. <hi>Hariſon,</hi> and the reſt of the Members of the late Supreme Authority of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> ſitting at <hi>Weſtm.</hi> had any real finger in it, or were actors of it, they may and ought all of them, with all the reſt under them, that have executed any part of the aforeſaid unjuſt, injurious, illegal Act of Parliament, to be apprehended, indicted, and proceeded againſt at the Common Law, as Traytors, and ſubverters of the Fundamental Laws, Liberties, and Freedoms of the free-born people of <hi>England;</hi> as that learned man in the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> in the ſecond, third, and fourth Parts of his Inſtitutes (all three of which are publiſhed by two ſpecial Orders of the late Houſe of Commons, in <hi>anno</hi> 1641. for good Laws) doth declare and prove was dealt with by <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118510:5"/>
in leſs caſes then the fore-recited unjuſt act of Baniſhment, and of which ſevere puniſhments thoſe Arbitrary and diſcretionary Judges, <hi>viz. Triſilian, Fulthrop, Belknap, Care, Holt, Burge,</hi> and <hi>Lockton,</hi> in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds time ſufficiently taſted of; as alſo their arbitrary Accomplices, the then Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon Burley,</hi> Sir <hi>William Ellinham,</hi> Sir <hi>John Salisbury,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Trevit,</hi> Sir <hi>James Barnis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Nicholas Dodgworth,</hi> ſome of whom were deſtroyed and hanged for ſetting their hands to Judgements in ſubverſion of the peoples fundamental Law and Liberties, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the Kings will above the ſame; yea one of them was baniſhed therefore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had a Dagger held unto his very breſt to compel him to ſet his hand thereto. But the two firſt mentioned perſons caſes being the moſt remarkable, the priſoner at the Bar ſhall only at preſent inlarge upon theirs.</p>
            <p>Which Caſe of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> was thus: At the Parliament holden by King, Lords, and Commons, in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſevenths time, who was an undoubted lawful king of <hi>England,</hi> and by his marriage of his wife, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> heir appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> as himſelf was to the houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> had united the two claimes of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> in himſelf, and in a pitcht battel had ſlaine King <hi>Richard</hi> the third the uſurper; and by reaſon of the extraordinary many troubles of his reign, and the ignorant Regal time in which he lived conſidered, he had a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more grounds to be arbitrary and diſcretionary in his proceedings with the people of <hi>England,</hi> then the late decapitated Parliament had; yet he ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a free Parliament, who ſate peaceably and quietly, without the force or purging of ſouldiers; and after that ſeveral Juries, at Aſſizes and Seſſions, by corruption and ſavour, had refuſed to finde perſons that were judicially proved guilty before them of breach of penal laws, as in full and free Parliament by King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, is avowedly declared, an Act of Parliament, (recorded in the fourth part of <hi>Cooks Inſtitutes,</hi> fol. 40. 41.) in the 11. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. was paſſed by King, Lords, and Commons, in full and free Parliament, to enable the Juſtices of Aſſize in open Seſſions to be holden before them, and the Juſtices of the Peace in each County in <hi>England,</hi> upon information for the King before them to be made, to have full power and authority by their diſcretion (without tryals by Juries) to hear and determine all offences and contempts committed againſt penal laws; in all which arbitrary or diſcretional proceedings, murther, treaſon, and felony, was excepted out of their cognizance or juriſdiction; as alſo all other offences whereby any perſon ſhould loſe life, or member, or lands, goods, or chattels to the party complaining. By pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of which Statute, ſaith the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his laſt recited <hi>folio, Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> (privy Councellors and Juſtices of Peace to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh) did commit upon the ſubject inſufferable preſſures and oppreſſions, which yet at the higheſt was but the taking away ſome ſmall part of the perſons eſtates from them that they condemned. And therefore this Statute was juſtly ſoon after the deceaſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, repealed at the next Parliament after his deceaſe, by the Statute of the 1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cha.</hi> 6. A good caveat, ſaith he, to Parliaments to leave all cauſes to be meaſured by the golden and ſtreight met-wand of the law, and not to the uncertaine and crooked cord of diſrcetion, for it is not almoſt credible to foreſee, ſaith he, when any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime, or fundamental law of this realm is altered, as elſewhere in the fourth part of Lord <hi>Cooks</hi> Reports hath been obſerved, what dangerous inconveniences do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; which moſt expreſly appeareth by this moſt unjuſt and ſtrange Act of 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. for hereby not only <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> themſelves, but ſuch Juſtices of Peace (cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt men) as they cauſed to be authorized, committed moſt grievous and heavy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and exactions, grinding the face of the poor ſubjects by penal laws (be they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118510:5"/>
never ſo obſolete or unfit for the time) by information onely, without any preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or trial by Jury, being the ancient birthright of the ſubject, but to hear and determine the ſame by their diſcretion, inflicting ſuch penalty, as the Statutes not repealed impoſed: theſe and other like actions and oppreſſions by, or by the means of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> and their inſtruments, brought infinite treaſures to the Kings Coffers, whereof the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng himſelf in the end, with great grief and compunction re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced, as in another place we have obſerved. This Statute of 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. We have recited, and ſhewed the juſt inconveniences thereof, to the end that the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke ſhould never hereafter be attempted in any court of Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ament; and that others might avoid the fearful end of thoſe two time-ſervers, <hi>Emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> and <hi>Dudley Qui corum v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtigia inſiſtant, corum exitus per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſcan,</hi> that is, thoſe that follow their footſteps may fear the ſame deſtruction that they had, whoſe end in the third part of the Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 208. and the fourth part, <hi>fol.</hi> 198, 199. may be ſeen, was ſeverally to be Indicted at common law (whoſe Indictments is there to be read) and convicted and executed as traitors, for ſubvert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the fundamental laws and liberties of <hi>England,</hi> viz. trials by Juries, which the Conqueſt of the <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Saxons, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Normans,</hi> could never blot out of the Kalender of Engliſh mens fundamental liberties, but hath from time to time, with the infinite hazards of their lives &amp; bloods been preſerved, as the choiceſt of their Jewels, and as one of their chiefeſt fundamental rights; of whom the ſaid L. <hi>Cook</hi> in his expoſition of the 29 Ch. of <hi>Magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Charta,</hi> in his 2 part Inſtit. <hi>fol.</hi> 51. upon the words of <hi>lex terrae,</hi> or the law of the land (where he plentifully ſhews, that no Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whatſoever, ought, for any Crime whatſoever, in any Court whatſoever, by any power or authority whatſoever, to be tryed but by juries, and due proceſs of law as is before ſhewed, expreſly ſaith, yet againſt the ancient &amp; fundamental las<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; in the face thereof, I finde an Act of Parliament made, ſaith he, that as well juſtices of Aſſize, as Juſtices of Peace (without any finding or preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment by the Verdict of twelve men) upon a bare information for the King, before them made, ſhould have full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority by their diſcretions, to hear and determine all offences and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts committed or done by any perſon or perſons, againſt the forme, ordinance and effect of any Statute made and not repeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by colour of which Act, ſhaking this fundamental law, it is not cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble what horrible oppreſſions and exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the undoing infinite numbers of people, were committed by Sir <hi>Richard Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> knight, and <hi>Edmund Dudley,</hi> being Juſtices of the Peace, throughout <hi>England,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this unjuſt and injurious Act (as commonly in like caſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t falleth out) a new of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was erected, and they made maſters of the Kings forfeitures. But at the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, holden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the firſt yeer of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, This Act of the 11. of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nry</hi> the ſeventh is rejected, and made void, and repeater, and the reaſon thereof is yeelded, for that by force of the ſaid act it was manifeſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nown, that many ſiniſter and crafty feigned forged informations, had been purſued aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt divers of the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs ſubjects, to their great damage and wrong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul vexations, and ill ſucceſs hereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: and the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ends of the two oppreſſors, ſhould deter others from c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, and ſhould admoniſh Parliaments, that in ſtead of the ordinary and precious trial <hi>per le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem terrae,</hi> by the law of the land, they bring not in abſolute an partial trial by diſcretion. And in the fourth part of his Inſtitutes, <hi>folio</hi> 37. he expreſly ſaith. That he findes an Attainder by Parliament of a ſubject (<hi>viz. Thomas Cromwel,</hi> then Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi>) of high treaſon, who was committed to the Tower, and thereby forth coming to be heard, and yet was never called to anſwer in any of the Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Of the manner of which proceedings, he thus ſaith, <hi>Auſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ſi non, ut cunque ſilontiam legat,</hi> That is, let the Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aments crime be buried in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118510:6"/>
oblivion if it be poſſible, and if not, nevertheleſs yet let it give place to ſilence for the preſent; for ſaith he, <hi>The more high and abſolute the juriſdiction of Court is, the more juſt and honorable it ought to be in the proceeding, and to give examples of juſtice to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Courts.</hi> And <hi>fol.</hi> 38. He is confidently perſwaded, that the rehearſeal of this unjuſt Attainder will hereafter cauſe the Honorable Members of both Houſes of Parliament to be ſo tender of their duty in perſerving the fundamental Laws and Liberties of the people of England, as that never hereafter ſuch an unjuſt Attainder ſhall be brought, where the party is forth coming to condemn him without hearing of him. And conſonant unto this, is the Scripture, and the Law of God therein contained, as appears by the third of <hi>Gen verſ.</hi> 9. where God after <hi>Adam</hi> had tranſgreſſed his law, ſummons him before him to anſwer for himſelf, before he would paſs judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. And when <hi>Sodom</hi> had abominably defiled its wayes with the height of wickedneſs, yet the juſt God of heaven and earth would not judge, condemne, or paſs ſentence againſt them, till he went down to ſee whether they have done alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether according to the cry that is come up againſt them or not and ſaith God, I will know, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18 and <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.6.11. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.15. God ſaith expreſly, One witneſs ſhall not riſe againſt a man for any iniquity, or for any ſin, in any ſin that he ſinneth; at the mouth of two witneſſes, or at the mouth of three witneſſes ſhall the matter be eſtabliſhed. And by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> he required the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to do according to the ſentence of the Law, and the judgement which ſhall be given thereupon, and not to decline from the law and the judgement which ſhall be given thereupon, and not to decline from the Law to the right hand or to the left. And ſuitable to this, is the judicial and legal proceedings of the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the children of Iſrael (conſiſting to the number of four thouſand able men) in the caſe of the Levite, and his raviſhed and ſlain concubine, who in their judicial proceedings in that caſe, firſt demanded of him how ſo great a wickedneſs came to be committed in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And the concluſion, after their hearing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the cauſe, was, to conſider, conſult, and then to give ſentence. And ſaith <hi>Nicodemus</hi> that learned man in the law of God, againſt the Scribes and Phariſees in behalf of Chriſt, <hi>Doth our law judge any man before it hear him and know what he doth?</hi> John 7.51. And ſaith <hi>Feſtus</hi> the heathen <hi>Roman</hi> Governour in <hi>Judea,</hi> that had no other guide to walk by, but the light and Law of Nature, In the behalf of <hi>Paul,</hi> againſt his bloody enemies, <hi>It is not the manner of the Romans to deliver any one to dye, before that he which is accuſed have the accuſers face to face, and have licenſe to anſwer for himſelf concerning the crime laid againſt him,</hi> Acts 25.16. And ſaith righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Paul,</hi> who writ the Oracles of God infallibly by the Spirit of God, <hi>Where there is no law, there is nor can be no tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 4.15. But ſaith that judicious and learned Lawyer Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in the third part of his Inſtitutes, <hi>folio</hi> 35. of <hi>Rhadamanthus,</hi> that cruel and wicked Judge of hell:</p>
            <p>Firſt, he puniſheth before he hears (like the late Parliament) and when he doth hear the denial, then he compels the party accuſed by torture to confeſs it: but, ſaith he, far otherwiſe doth Almighty God proceed; for after that the guilty perſon is accuſed, he calls, he examines, and then judges or condemns, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.1, 2. But in his fourth part Inſtitutes, he proceeds and goeth on, and ſaith in his laſt fore-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited <hi>folio,</hi> As evil was the proceedings in Parliament, in the ſecond of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. Number 18. againſt Sir <hi>John Mortimer,</hi> the third ſon of <hi>Edmund</hi> the ſecond Earle of <hi>Marſh</hi> (deſcended from <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi>) who was Indicted of high treaſon, for certaine words, which Indictment (without any arraignment or pleading) being meerly feigned to blemiſh the title of the Mortimers, and withall being inſufficient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118510:6"/>
in law, as by the ſame appeareth, was confirmed by authority of Parliament, and the ſaid Sir <hi>John</hi> being brought into the Parliament, without arraignment and anſwer, judgement in Parliament was given againſt him upon the ſaid Indictment, that he ſhould be carried to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and drawn through the City to <hi>Tiburn,</hi> and there hanged, drawn and quartered, his head to be ſet on <hi>London-bridge,</hi> his four quarters on the four gates of <hi>London,</hi> as by the Record of Parliament ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. And therefore, in the next <hi>folio,</hi> being <hi>folio</hi> 39. he ſaith, that whereas by order of Law, a man cannot be attainted of high treaſon, unleſs the offence be in law high treaſon: he ought not to be attained by general words of high treaſon, <hi>By authority of Parliament</hi> (as ſometime hath been uſed) but the high treaſon ought to be ſpecially expreſſed, ſeeing that the Court of Parliament, is the higheſt and moſt honorable Court of Juſtice, and ought (as hath been ſaid) to give examples to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Courts. And further, to ſhew that Parliaments (which in their right conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are the beſt conſervators of our laws and liberties) are erroneous things (when they walk by their own wills) and forſake their true and only guide, the fundamental laws of <hi>England</hi>) What need there any more inſtances then many of the Armies own Declarations, in ſeveral of which and their frequent diſcourſes they have declared the late Parliament a traiterous Parliament, breakers of their truſt, and imbroyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Nation in bloody wars, and ſubverters of the peoples liberties and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; yea, and in the concluſion, the Lord General <hi>Cromwel</hi> himſelf, and Major Gen. <hi>Hariſon,</hi> with their own hands have pulled them out by the ears, and pluckt them up by the very roots, as final breakers of their truſt; and as a pack of the vileſt knaves and villaines that ever breathed in <hi>England,</hi> although they were fenced in, and about by an Act of Parliament made before the wars, by King, Lords, and Commons, in the ſeventeenth of the raigne of the late King (being in the yeer 1641) that they ſhould not be diſſolved, but by their own free and voluntary conſents. And alſo, ſince they changed the Kingdome into a Commonwealth, by two ſeveral Acts of Parliament of the 14. of <hi>May,</hi> 1649. and the 17. of <hi>July</hi> 1649. In which it is expreſly made high treaſon, for any Engliſhman, or men, by writing, printing, or words declaring, or by endeavouring to raiſe or ſtir up force to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the late Parliament, or their Councel of State, without their own conſents, or to ſay that the ſaid late Parliament or their Councel of State is tyrannical, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, or unlawful, as by the ſaid Acts of Parliament, with reference thereunto being had, more at large doth appear (which Acts are printed in the firſt part of the trial or arraignment of the priſoner at the Bar, at <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> Oct. 1649. pag. 86, 87<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 88, 89. the firſt of which Acts, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the 14. of <hi>May,</hi> 1649. thus followeth Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
                        <head>An Act Declaring what offences ſhall be adjudged Treaſon.</head>
                        <p>WHereas the Parliament hath aboliſhed the the Kingly Office in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging; and hath reſolved and declared, that the people ſhall for the future be govern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d by its own Repreſentatives, or national meetings in councel, choſen and intruſted by them for that purpoſe, hath ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tled the Government in the way of a Commonwealth and free State, without King or Houſe of Lords; Be it Enacted by this preſent Parliament, and by the Authority of the ſame, That if any perſon ſhall maliciouſly or adviſedly publiſh, by writing, printing, or openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, That the ſaid Government is tyrannical, uſurped, or unlawful; or that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118510:7"/>
in Parliament aſſembled are not the Supream Authority of this Nation; or ſhall plot, contrive, or indeavor o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſtir up, or raiſe force againſt the preſent government, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> for the ſubverſion or alteration of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and ſhall declare the ſame by any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>n de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d, that then every ſuch ofence ſhal be taken, deemed, and adjudged by the Authority of this Parliament to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> high treaſon. And whereas the Keepers of the liberties of <hi>England,</hi> and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State, conſtruted, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>om time to time conſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> by A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>uo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>y of Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt are to be under the ſaid R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>preſentatives in Parliament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> for the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ce of the ſaid government, with ſeveral powers and Authorities limited, given and appo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m by the Parliament; Be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> likewiſe Enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f any perſon ſhall maliciouſly and adviſedly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o or indeavor the ſubverſion of the ſaid Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the liberties of <hi>England</hi> or the Counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l of State, and the ſame ſhall declare by any op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſhall move any perſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſons fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ng ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>of, or ſtir up the people to riſe againſt them, or eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r of them, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> or ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>her of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>horities, That then every ſum off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nces ſhall be tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>med and a clored to be high treaſon, And w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>as the Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> for their juſt and lawful def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nce, hath raiſed, levied the Army and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>es now under the command of <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> preſent neceſſitated, by reaſon of the manifold diſtractions with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n this commonwealth, and invaſions threatned from abroad, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o continue the ſame, which under God muſt be the inſtrumental means of preſerving the well-afflicted p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>opl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of this Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>on in peace and ſafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y, Be it further Enacted by the aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y aforeſaid, that if any perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o being an Officer, Souldier, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Member of the Army, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o, contrive, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> indeavour to ſtir up any mutiny in the ſaid Army, or withdraw any Souldiers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Officers from their obedience to their ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Officers, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> from the preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt Governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt as afo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſaid; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſhall procure, invite, and, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> aſſiſt any fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>raigners or ſtrangers to invade <hi>England</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Ireland:</hi> or ſhall adhere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o any forces raiſed by the enemies of the Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> or Common wealth, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England:</hi> Or if any perſon ſhall counterfeit the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> (for the time being) uſed and appointed by authority of Parliament, That th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uch offence and off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nces ſhall be taken, deemed, and declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the authority of this Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt to be high-treaſon; and every ſuch perſon ſhall ſuffer pains of death, and alſo forfeit un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o the Keepers of the Liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y of <hi>England,</hi> to and for the uſe of the Commonwealth, all and ſingular his and their lands, ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, goods and chattels, as in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of high-treaſon hath been uſed by the Laws and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>is land to be forfeit and loſt. Provided always, that no perſons ſhall be indicted and arraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d for any of the off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nces mentioned in this Act, unleſs ſuch offenders ſhall be indicted or proſecuted for the ſame within one yeer after the offence committed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Die Lunae, 14 Maii, 1649.</hi>
                              </date> Ordered by the Parliament, That this Act be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</dateline>
                           <signed>Hen. Scobel, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
                  <back>
                     <div type="colophon">
                        <p>
                           <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw. Husband</hi> &amp; <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to the Parl. of <hi>England. 1649</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </back>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> now priſoner at the Bar, for further Plea ſaith, that for ſuppoſed violating thoſe two laſt fore-mentioned Acts of Parliament, and that but for ſuppoſed words, and for the ſuppoſed comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling, writing, and cauſed to be printed Arguments, founded and grounded upon the known and declared fundamental laws of <hi>England,</hi> received principles of Reaſon, and the Armies own pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted and publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhed Declarations, he the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> now priſoner at the bar, was arra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gned and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted as a Traytor for his lite at <hi>Guild-hall London,</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1649. and that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally by the inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gation and means of his Excellencie the preſent Lord General <hi>Cromwel:</hi> which Tryal was with that violence and fury, that the ſaid priſoner at the Bar was abſolutely denyed the declared benefit of the known laws of <hi>England, viz.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118510:7"/>
the help of Counſel learned in the Law, and a copie of his Charge and Indictment, which were not denied, but granted to the Lord <hi>Mocqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that grand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>be; and thoſe Arch-trayt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, as the yeare commonly called, <hi>Scraſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c, Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>bury, Hamilton,</hi> and <hi>Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> &amp;c. which alſo was granted to the priſoner at Bar as his right by Law, when he was pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ner a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>agned by judge <hi>Heart,</hi> &amp;c. for his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as a traytor So that the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the bar, conſidering, the ſeveral penalties declared to be due to any perſon or perſons whatſoever, that by force or otherwiſe ſhould but endeavour to diſſolve the late Parliament or their Councel of State, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cannot either in Reaſon or Law ſee or apprehend which way his Excellency the ſaid Lord General <hi>Cromw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> and Major General <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon,</hi> &amp;c. if they continue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere as they have begun, to execute the ſaid unjuſt and injurious Act of Parliament upon the ſaid <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Lilbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> priſoner at the Bar, (which is one of the moſt wickedſt and unjuſt that ever the Parliament in their lives made, and of the higheſt and moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious acts of their breach of truſt that ever they committed, as is before fully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the leaſt, either before God or men, acquit themſelves of being guilty of the higheſt of treaſon, both by the letter and equity of the two laſt fore-mentioned. Laws lately made in part by themſelves, but principally by their inſtigation, in forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly diſſolving the late Parliament, againſt their own voluntary wills and conſents.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> the now priſoner at the bar, for further plea ſaith, That it is moſt juſt, equitable, and reaſonable, to indict, arraign, condemn, and execute the foreſaid declared Parliament Traytors, <hi>Olive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cromwel</hi> Eſquire, Captain General, and Mr. <hi>Thomas Hariſon,</hi> commonly called Major-General <hi>Hariſon,</hi> before the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the bar be indicted, arraigned, condemned, and executed, for being a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Parliament felon, eſpecially conſidering their tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>greſſions is a fact committed after the declaring, printing, and divulging of a viſible and plain Law; and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the Bar's ſuppoſed crime is for a fact done before there was a Law in being, as in ſearching into the bottom of the whole illegal proceedings aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt him will evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly appear. 2. The priſoner at the bar's tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>greſſion, at moſt, is but a ſuppoſed or a real ſcandal of one Member of Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> in which at moſt he was but of Counſel for Mr. <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mate,</hi> upon a Petitionary Appeal; which <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate,</hi> at the open Bar of the Parliament, freed <hi>John Lilburne</hi> the now priſoner at the Bar from drawing his ſaid Petition at which the Parliament took the offence, and at whoſe Bar he avowedly layd the draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of it upon another; and yet the priſoner at the Bar muſt be thought worthy to be baniſhed, and robbed by Sir <hi>Arthur Hazle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> of all his eſtate, that at the moſt was but an acceſſary to a ſcandal, and <hi>Primate</hi> the principal, that owned the Petition for his, and juſtified the printing of it by his own order, hath no ſuch puniſhment at all inflicted upon him n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor yet his Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el that he avowed drew it. But the crime of the ſaid <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> Lord General, and Major-Gen. <hi>Hariſon,</hi> in forcibly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſolving the Parliament, is not onely a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing of one Member of Parliament, but of all the Members thereof, as a pack of Rogues, and traytors to their truſt, and thereby fit for nothing, but to be knockt on the head by the enraged people where-ever they meet them, and as unſavoury ſalt, that is good for nothing, but to be pluckt our by the ears, and pluckt up by the roots, and thrown to the dunghil. 3. The Parliaments Laws were either good and juſt, or they were not If good and juſt, why were they that made them pluckt up by the roots, and diſſolved without their free conſents, and that by their hired ſervants, that had no power either in Law or from the people ſo to do, and upon whom out of the peoples moneys they have beſtowed many thouſand pounds gratuities? If they were wicked and unjuſt, why is the baſeſt and vileſt of them endeavoured to be executed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118510:8"/>
upon the priſoner at the Bar for ſuppoſed Felony, and that principally by the means of thoſe, that both by the letter and equity of the ſaid Parliaments Laws, are guilty of higheſt of treaſons, in diſſolving the Parliament by force of Arms, without their own free conſents; and who have been, and yet are, the only &amp; principal proſecutors of me the priſoner at the Bar for his life, for returning into the land of his Nativity (againſt the Fundamental Laws &amp; Liberties, which in all his days he never committed the leaſt tranſgreſſion) after he was forced, by reaſon of Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerig</hi>'s robbing him of all his eſtate, for divers months together, to borrow all the money that bought him bread, and after he had continued about a yeer &amp; a half in conſtant danger of his life, of being murdered beyond the Seas, by the hands of the mad or ranting Cavaliers, by the cunning artifice and deſignes of the penſioned Agents of ſome of the principalleſt of thoſe that moſt in Parliament ſtudied his Baniſhment, yet in which Act that they pretend to baniſh one Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> by, there is no crime of Law at all in Law layd unto the ſayd Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi>'s charge (generals being no crimes in law, nor ſignifie nothing, as fully appears by the Lord <hi>Cook</hi>'s ſecond part of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 52, 315, 318, 590, 591, 615, 616. and third part, <hi>fol.</hi> 12, 13, 14. and fourth part, <hi>fol.</hi> 39, 333, 334.) as appears by the Act it ſelf, which thus <hi>verbatim</hi> followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
                        <head>An Act for the execution of a Judgement given in Parliament againſt Lieut. Col. <hi>JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>WHereas upon the fifteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred fifty one, Judgement was given in Parliament againſt the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> for high Crimes and Miſdemeanours by him committed, relating to a falſe, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and ſcandalous Petition heretofore preſented to the Parliament by one <hi>Joſiah Primate</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Leather ſeller, as by the due proceedings had upon the ſaid Petition, and the Judgement thereupon given, at large appeareth: Be it therefore Enacted by this preſent Parliament, and by the authority of the ſame, That the Fine of three thouſand pounds impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> to the uſe of the Commonwealth, by the Judgement afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall be forthwith levied by due Proces of Law to the uſe of the commonwealth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. And be it further enacted, That the ſum of two thouſand pounds impoſed by the ſaid Judgement upon the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> to be paid to <hi>James Ruſſel, Edw. Winſlow, William Molins,</hi> and <hi>Arthur Squib,</hi> in the ſaid Judgement named, that is to ſay, to each of them five hundred pounds for their damages, ſhall be forthwith paid accordingly: And that the ſaid Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerig, James Ruſſel, Edw. Winſlow, William Molins,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Squib,</hi> their Executors and Adminiſtrators, ſhall have the like remedy and proceedings at Law reſpectively againſt the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> his Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſignes, for the recovery of the ſaid reſpective ſums ſo given to them by the ſaid Judgment, as if the ſaid reſpective ſums had been due by ſeveral Recognizances in the nature of a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-ſtaple acknowledged unto them ſeverally by the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> upon the ſaid <hi>15</hi> day of <hi>January 1651.</hi> And be it likewiſe enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> ſhall within twenty days, to be accounted from the ſaid fifteenth day of <hi>January 1651.</hi> depart out of <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and the Iſlands, Territories, or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions thereof. And in caſe the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> at any time after the expiration of the ſaid twenty days to be accounted as aforeſaid, ſhall be found or ſhall be remaining within <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> or within any of the Iſlands, Territories, or Dominions thereof the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> ſhall be, and is hereby adjudged a Felon, and ſhall be executed as a Felon, without benefit of Clergie. And it is laſtly enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> all and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> and perſons who ſhall after the expiration of the ſaid twenty days accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118510:8"/>
harbour, or conceal the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> he being in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or any of the Territories, Iſlands, or Dominions thereof, ſhall be hereby adjudged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary of Felony after the fact. And all Judges, Juſtices, Maiors, Bayliffs, Sheriffs, and all other Officers, as well Military as Civil, in their reſpective places, are hereby required to be aiding and aſſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ng in apprehending the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>1651. </hi>
                              </date>
                              <hi>Ordered by the Parliament, That this Act be forthwith printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</hi>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Hen. Scobel, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Fourthly, the priſoner at the Bar's return into <hi>England</hi> tends not in the leaſt to the diſturbance of the publike peace, quietneſs, or tranquillity of the Nation, nor to the deſtruction and overthrow of all the Peoples Fundamental liberties and freedoms; and therefore no reaſons at all can be drawn from publike utility or profit to try me <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the bar for his life as a Felon, upon the unjuſt letter of a void Act of Parliament. But as for the ſaid Generals, and the ſaid Major-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Hariſons</hi> diſſolving the late Parliament by force, againſt their own conſents, and thereby againſt ſeveral Acts of Parliament afore mentioned (partly of their own making) committing high-treaſon againſt the apparent letter of a known, printed, and declared Law, before their fact committed; out of which evil action (as it is in it ſelf ſimply conſidered) though it be granted, that that God that can and hath brought light out of darkneſs, and order out of confuſion, and good out of evil, may out of it, by his wiſdom, power, and omnipotencie, bring abundance of good to this poor nation of <hi>England;</hi> yet already it hath viſibly produced this grand miſchief and evil, <hi>viz.</hi> to give the ſaid General a colourable pretence of a Neceſſity of his own making and creating, to aſſume unto himſelf all the Civil powers in the Nation into his own hands; and thereby not onely to make ſlaves (if he pleaſe) of all his own private ſouldiers, in ſubjecting them to Tryals for their lives by Military or arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diſcipline in times of peace, when all the Courts of Juſtice for adminiſtring the Law are or ought to be open, which is expreſly againſt the Petition of Right, and the declared end wherefore the Wars were engaged in againſt the late King; but alſo of the free people of <hi>England,</hi> that have fought as heartily and faithfully for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Liberties and Freedoms as himſelf, who have already thereby loſt two of the chiefeſt of their fundamental rights and freedoms, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to have Taxes layd upon them by the General, with the advice of his Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Officers, all of whom at moſt are but the peoples hired and payd ſervants, to kill the Weaſels and Polecats that would deſtroy their Liberties; which is not onely contrary to the expreſs tenour of that moſt excellent Law (as the late Parliament, in their remarkable Declaration of <hi>March</hi> 17. 1648. calls it) of the Petition of Right, which expreſly ſayth, <hi>That no Taxes, Ayds, or Contributions whatever, ſhall by any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, or any Authority whatſoever, be layd or levyrd upon the people, but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent of their choſen Deputies or Truſtees in Parliament aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbled for that end.</hi> See alſo the Lord <hi>Cooks</hi> 4 part Inſtitutes, <hi>chap. High Court of Parliament, fol.</hi> 14, 34. and by the Statute made in the late Parliament, in the 17 yeer (being <hi>anno</hi> 1641) of the late King, intituled, <hi>An Act for declaring unlawful and void the late proceedings touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ship money.</hi> The Judgement of the Judges in that caſe is declared null and void, and againſt the right of Proprieties, although their judgements were grounded upon theſe plauſible Queſtions, <hi>viz. That when the good and ſafety of the Kingdom in general is concerned, and the whole Kingdom in danger, Whether the King might by writ under the Great Seal of England command all the Subjects of his Kingdom at their charge to provide and furniſh ſuch number of Ships, with Men, Victuals, and Munition, and for ſuch a time
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118510:9"/>
as the King ſhould think fit, for the defence and ſafeguard of the kingdom from ſuch peril and danger:</hi> and, <hi>Whether by Law the King might compel the doing thereof, in caſe of refuſal or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>actari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs. And whether that the King</hi> (who was then a far more legal Magiſtrate then the Lord General <hi>Cromwel</hi> now is) <hi>were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judge both of the danger, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow the ſame is to be prevented and avoided.</hi> According to which grounds and reaſons, all the juſtices of the ſaid Courts of K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs Bench, and Common pleas, and the ſaid Barons of the Exchequer, having been formerly con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d with by his Majeſties command, had ſet their hands to an extrajudicial Opinion expreſſed to the ſame purpoſe, That he might: and yet notwithſtanding all this, thus decreed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by all the judges, all ſuch Ship-writes and all proceedings thereupon are by King, Lords, and Commons, in full, legal, and free Parliament, declared that they were and are contrary and againſt the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, and the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Right made in the third yeer of the Reign of his Majeſty that then was. And it is there further declared and enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the particulars prayed or deſired in the ſaid Petition of Right, ſhall from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be put in execution accordingly, and ſhall be firmly and ſtrictly holden and obſerved, as in the ſame Petition they are prayed and expreſſed: And that all the ſaid Judgements and Proceedings about the ſaid Ship money be vacated and cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. One of the makers of which Law was the ſaid <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> now Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and alſo one of the impeachers of the ſaid Ship money-Judges of high-trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for arbitrary ſubverters of the free people of <hi>England</hi>'s fundamental Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Proprieties.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the General, with whom of his Officers by his will he is pleaſed to joyn with him, hath not onely by their late forcible diſſolving of the late Parliament, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the whole Civil power of the Nation into his own hands; by means of which already, by his Declaration with the advice of his Office<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, of the 9 of <hi>June</hi> 1653. he hath arbitrarily layd a Tax of Sixſcore thouſand pounds <hi>per</hi> month upon the free people of <hi>England,</hi> by which all their proprieties are confounded and deſtroyed. For, by the ſame Rule that he lays Sixſcore thouſand pounds Tax a month upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he may (when he pleaſeth) lay ſix Millions a month upon them, and ſo <hi>ad infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum;</hi> and ingroſs into his own coffers and hands, and his Officers, not onely all the peoples treaſure, but alſo their whole lands and eſtates, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did the ſlaviſh E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians unto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Gen 47. but that which is worſe, he hath not onely there by created a preſident to deſtroy all their proprieties, but his chuſing the people Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Law-makers, (though it's poſſible the men may prove in their actions the juſteſt men in the Nation) and denying thoſe that never forfeited their Liberties in their lives, that inherent and natural right, he hath created a preſident to deſtroy their Laws, Liberties, and Lives, and abſolutely ſubject them to his will and mercy: which crimes put together, are in the eye of the Law the higheſt Treaſon that ever I read any tranſgreſſor in the Nation charged with, ever ſince it became a Politick So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety or Nation, and an act that the higheſt of three Tyrants or Conquerors, either under the Romanes, Saxons, Danes, or Normans, durſt never attempt to put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution: By means of which, he hath given away the juſt and honeſt Cauſe betwixt the King and Parliament, and done as much as in him hath to make all thoſe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers that have ſince the beginning of the late Civil war engaged in the Parliament-quarrel againſt the late King, his actions as evidently as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un declaring it was not in the leaſt for the ſecuring of the peoples incroached upon Liberties and Freedoms, that he and his accomplices took up Arms againſt the King for, but to pull him out of his Throne, ſlay him, and divide his inheritance amongſt him and his accomplices,
<pb facs="tcp:118510:9"/>
and then to ſet up his luſt, will, and pleaſure, as the peoples ſtanding Laws. By which apparent, and in the face of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un avowed practices of his, he hath all over the Chriſtian world brought more ſcorn and contempt upon the zealous profeſſion of God and godlineſs, and all the pretences of ſtrugling for Liberty and Freedom, then any one man that ever I read of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all the Hiſtories of the world that ever my eyes were fixed upon: yea, and in the doing of the forementioned things, hath given in the face of the ſun the abſolute and perfect lye to himſelf, and all his many prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Declarations, both as he is to be conſidered as a Parliament-man, or as an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in Arms. And firſt, conſider him as a Parliament-man, how many Oaths, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Proteſtations, and Engagements, hath he formerly taken, to maintain the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws and Liberties of the people of <hi>England;</hi> and alſo, after he had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Parliament to be purged over and over, again and again, and left none to ſit there, but thoſe that then pleaſed his tooth, and by their authority taken away the Kings life, and altered the form of Government nominally into a Commonwealth or free State, did not he and his ſaid friends or Councellors immediately after that publiſh a ſolemn Declaration of <hi>Febr.</hi> 9. 1648. in theſe very words <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <head>A Declaration of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> for maintaining the Fundamental Laws of this Nation.</head>
                        <p>THe Parliament of <hi>England</hi> now aſſembled doth declare, That they are fully reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to maintain, and ſhall and will uphold, preſerve, and keep the fundamental Laws of this Nation, for and concerning the preſervation of the lives, properties, and liberties of the people, with all things incident thereunto, with the alterations touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kings and Houſe of Lords already reſolved in this preſent Parliament, for the good of the people, and what ſhall be further neceſſary for the perfecting thereof; and do require and expect that all Judges, Juſtices, Sheriffs, and all Officers and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Juſtice for the time being, do adminiſter juſtice, and do proceed in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective places and Offices accordingly: which reſolution, with the reaſons thereof, ſhall be hereafter publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſhed in a larger Declaration touching the ſame. And it is hereby ordered and appointed, that this Declaration ſhall be forthwith proclaimed in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, and at the Old Exchange: and the Judges in their reſpective Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and at the firſt ſitting thereof, are to cauſe this Declaration to be publikely read. And the Sheriffs in their ſeveral Counties are to cauſe this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to be likewiſe publiſhed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Veneris, 9 <hi>February,</hi> 1648.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <hi>Ordered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That this Declaration be forthwith prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and publiſhed; and that the Members of this Houſe do take care to diſperſe the ſaid Declaration into the ſeveral Counties with all ſpeed.</hi> 
                           <signed>H. Scobel, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
                  <back>
                     <div type="colophon">
                        <p>
                           <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Husbands.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </back>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Which ſaid Declaration was backed alſo with a large &amp; pithy one, the 17 of <hi>March</hi> 1648. which expreſſeth the grounds and reaſons of their late proceedings, and ſetling the preſent Government in way of a Free State.</p>
            <p>Yea, <hi>John Lilburn</hi> now priſoner at the bar for his further plea ſaith, That by the Act of the late Parliament intituled, <hi>An Act for the aboliſhing the Kingly Office in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions thereunto belonging,</hi> it is there amongſt other things enacted and declared, that the Office of a King in this Nation ſhall not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth reſide in, or be exerciſed by any one ſingle perſon. And that no perſon whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall or may have or hold the office, ſtile, dignity, power, or authority of King of the ſaid Dominions, or any of them, upon pain of high treaſon againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and People of <hi>England,</hi> to all ſuch ſaid perſons, and to all their aiders, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſters, comforters or abettors.</p>
            <p>Now whether or no that the ſaid actions of laying Taxes, and chuſing the people Law makers, be not the abſolute exerciſing the office, dignity, power, and authority of the greateſt King that ever was in <hi>England,</hi> the priſoner at the Bar ſubmits it to
<pb facs="tcp:118510:10"/>
the judgement of the learned Judges of the Law.</p>
            <p>And in the laſt forementioned Act, it is further declared and averred, that by the aboliſhing of the Kingly Office, a moſt happie way is made for this Engliſh Nation to return to its juſt and ancient rights of being governed by its own Repreſentatives, or National Meetings in Councel, from time to time choſen and intruſted for that purpoſe by the people. And further it is therefore there reſolved and declared by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That they will put a period to the ſitting of this preſent Parliament, and diſſolve the ſame, as ſoon as may poſſibly ſtand with the ſafety of the people that hath betruſted them, &amp; with what is abſolutely neceſſary for the preſerving and upholding the Government now ſetled in the way of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. And that they will carefully provide for the certain meeting chuſing &amp; ſitting of the next and future Repreſentatives, with ſuch other circumſtances of freedom in choice, and equality in diſtribution of Members to be elected thereunto, as ſhall moſt conduce to the laſting freedom and good of this Commonwealth. And in ſeveral other Acts immediately made after the laſt forementioned Acts; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe two Acts of Parliament of the 14 of <hi>May</hi> and the 17 of <hi>June</hi> 1649. decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what offences ſhall be judged treaſon, it is thus expreſſed: <hi>Whereas the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath aboliſhed the Kingly Office in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and in the dominions and territories thereunto belonging, and hath reſolved and declared that the people ſhall for the future be governed by its own Repreſentatives, or National Meetings in Councel, choſen and intruſted by them for that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Priſoner at the Bar for further plea in the ſecond place ſaith, that his Declarations as a Souldier or Commander to this purpoſe are ſo full as more can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid; and particularly that remarkable Declaration of the 14 of <hi>June</hi> 1647. printed in the Armies Book of Declar. p. 36. 37. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which 37. p. there he poſitively declares that the ſetling of the liberties, and freedoms, and peace of the Nation is the bleſſing of God, then which of all worldly things, nothing (ſay they) is more dear unto us, or more precious in our thoughts; we having hitherto thought all our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoments (whether of live or livelihood, or neareſt relations) a price but ſufficient to the puchaſe of ſo rich a bleſſing, that we and all the free-borne people of this Nation may ſit downe in quiet under our Vines, and under the glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of juſtice and righteouſneſs, and in full poſſeſſion of thoſe fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal rights and liberties, without which we can have little hopes (as to humane conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations) to enjoy either any comforts of life, or ſo much as life it ſelf, but at the pleaſures of ſome men ruling meerly according to will and power. And therein, pag. 43. they declared it is their earneſt deſire, that ſome determinate period of time may be ſet for the countinuance of this and future Parliaments, beyond which none ſhall continue, and upon which new Writs may of courſe iſſue out, and new Elections ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively take place, according to the intent of the Bil for triennial Parliaments; which Bill or Act being one of the firſt Laws paſt by the late Parliament, in the year 1640. Expreſly by name in divers places of it declares it is the undoubted right of the Freeholders, Citizens, and other Free-borne perſons of <hi>England,</hi> to elect ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as they pleaſe for their Repreſentors in the Parliament or Common counſel of the Nation, as at large appears by the Act it ſelf, reference thereunto being had; Unto which the priſoner at the Bar for further confirmation referreth himſelf, and in his, and the Officers of the Armies large Declaration for tryal of the late King, dated at St. <hi>Albons November,</hi> 1948. they in page 14. 15. thus declare themſelves; that the ſum of the publique intereſt of the Nation, in relation to common right and freedom (which they there a vow to be the chief ſubject of their conteſt with the King) and in oppoſition to tyranny and injuſtice of Kings or others they judge to lye.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that all matters of ſupream truſt or concernment to the ſafety and welfare of the whole, they have a common and ſupreme counſel of Parliament, and that (as to he common behalf, who cannot all meet together themſelves) to conſiſt of Deputies
<pb facs="tcp:118510:10"/>
or Repreſentors freely choſen by them with as much equality as may be: and after in that Remonſtrance, they have made large Declarations of divers things for the good of the people of <hi>England,</hi> in pag. 65. they deſired that the Parliament would ſet ſome reaſonable and certain period to their power and ſitting; by which time (ſay they) That great and ſupream truſt repoſed in you, ſhall be returned in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the hands of the people, from, and for whom you received it, that ſo you may give them ſatisfaction and aſſurance, that what you have contended for againſt the King (for which they have been put to ſo much trouble, coſt, and loſs of blood) hath been onely for their liberties, and common intereſt, and not for your owne perſonal inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <p>And in the next page, being pag. 66. they vehemently preſs for the equal diſtribution of elections thereunto, to render the houſe of Commons as near as may be, an equal Repreſentative of the whole people electing; and they there alſo preſs, for the eſtabliſhing a certainty for the peoples meeting to elect, and for their full freedome in election, provided that none who have engaged, or ſhall engage in war againſt the right of Parliament and intereſt of the kingdome therein, or have adhered to the enemies thereof, may be capable of electing, or being elected (at leaſt during a competent number of years) nor any other who ſhall oppoſe, or not joyne in agreement to this ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and in the next pag. being 67. In their firſt head, they deſire liberty of entring diſſents in the ſaid Repreſentatives, that in caſe of corruption, or abuſe in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of higheſt truſt, the people may be in capacity to know who are free thereof, and who guilty, to the end onely the people may avoid the future truſting of ſuch: and ſutable to theſe heads and others of publique freedome there laid downe, the ſaid General <hi>Cromwel</hi> and the reſt of his Officers, concluded upon a plat-form of Government, for the ſecuring the future liberties and freedomes of the people in all the aforeſaid concernments; and intituled it, An Agreement prepared for the people of <hi>England,</hi> and the places there incorporated, which was with ſeriouſneſs preſented by Lieut. General <hi>Hamond,</hi> Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> and other Officers of the Army to the Parliament upon the 20 of <hi>January</hi> 1649. as the ſum of all they had been fighting for, and all that which they deſired to eſtabliſh for the future good of the Nation; as more at large doth appear by the printed Model of the ſaid agreement; reference thereunto being had, and unto which for further ſatisfaction the priſoner at the Bar refers himſelf.</p>
            <p>And in the Generals laſt Declaration of <hi>April</hi> 22 laſt, p. 6. there he declares it his earneſt deſire to reform the Law, and adminiſter juſtice impartially, hoping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the people might forget Monarchy; and underſtanding their true intereſt in the election of ſucceſſive Parliaments, may have the Government ſetled upon a true Baſis.</p>
            <p>And the priſoner at the Bar for further plea ſaith, That he cannot ſee or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how the ſaid Lord General, or Major-General <hi>Hariſon,</hi> can, if they continue and perſevere as they have begun, to execute the ſaid unjuſt and injurious Act of Parliament upon the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> priſoner at the Bar (which is one of the moſt wicked and unjuſt that ever the Parliament in their lives made, and one of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt notorious acts of their breach of truſt that ever they committed, as is before fully proved) can in the leaſt, either before God or man, acquit themſelves of being guilty of the higheſt Treaſons, both by the letter and equity of the two fore-mentioned Laws of the 14 of <hi>May</hi> and the 17 of <hi>June</hi> 1649. lately made in part by themſelves, but principally by their inſtigators, in forcibly diſſolving the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt their own voluntary wills and conſents; or how they can acquit themſelves in the leaſt, in the eyes of all the underſtanding people in <hi>England,</hi> to be juſtly eſteemed guilty of plucking up the Parliament by the roots, not in the leaſt for evil, oppreſſion, injuſtice, or breach of truſt they had committed againſt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or honeſt people thereof, (that never yet in the leaſt, upon their own principles, forfeited their Liberties and Freedoms) but onely becauſe they would deſtroy the
<pb facs="tcp:118510:11"/>
Parliament, to have the power in their own hands, thereby to diſpoſe of all the lives, liberties, and proprieties of all the people of <hi>England,</hi> by then abſolute wills and pleaſures, and to deal worſe and in arbitrarily with the honeſt inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then any Conqueror that every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n before them did, although themſelves, againſt the late King, have in <hi>The K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtated,</hi> p. 22. by <hi>John Cook</hi> their own Atturney-General publikely declared, <hi>That Conqueſt is a Title o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Government fit to be exerciſed amongſt Bears and Wolves, but gol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt among men.</hi> And for any to aver us in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be a conquered Nation, is not onely expreſly againſt the tenour of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies many and remarkable Declarations, but it is ſuch an averment, then which there can be none more pregnant and fruitful in Treaſon then it, as Mr. <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ym</hi> in his learned and rational printed Argument, by the ſpecial Order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, the 29 of <hi>April</hi> 1641. againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> avers. And further, in pag. 6. ſaith, There are few Nations in the world that have not been conquered: and no doubt but the Conquerour may give what Laws he pleaſe to thoſe that are conquered; but if the ſucceeding pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Agreements do not limit and reſtraine that right, what people can be ſecure? <hi>England</hi> hath been conquered, and <hi>Wales</hi> hath been conquered; and by this reaſon will be in little better caſe then <hi>Ireland:</hi> if the King by the right of a Conquerour give Lawes to his people, ſhall not the people by the ſame reaſon be reſtored to the right of the Conquered, to recover their liberty if they can? what can be more hurtfull, more pernicious to both, then ſuch propoſitions as theſe, which muſt needs be moſt truely averred, have no end of blood ſhed and murder, and all the miſeries beſides that tongue can expreſs, or heart can imagine? And it is impoſſible that ever the honeſt people of <hi>England</hi> ſhould intruſt (as in ſome meaſure they have done) the General and his Officers with the cuſtody, and preſervation of their lives, liberties, freedoms, and proprieties, with any the leaſt intention, that when they had ſubdued their common enemies, they ſhould ſubdue their fundamental laws and rights (for the preſervation of which, the only conteſt with the common enemy was begun) and then give them a law flowing from their uncertain diſcretionary wills and pleaſures. Sure I am, that righteous and juſt <hi>David</hi> calls thoſe ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> and wicked men, that would go about to deprive thoſe that ſtayed with the ſtuff of an equal ſhare in the Conqueſt, even with thoſe that went out to fight, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.21, 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And righteous and juſt <hi>Abraham,</hi> out of his affection to his brother <hi>Lot,</hi> ventured his life by fore of Arms, to redeem him from his captivity, and with him redeemed the people of the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and their goods, after they were overthrown in pitcht battel: after which valiant and friendly ſervice, the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> intreated of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to give him the perſons, and to take the goods to himſelf: unto which the righteous man an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers (although the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> was an al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en and ſtranger to him and all his, and all that he had taken was by our preſent Chriſtian Souldiers Marſhal-law good priz) I have lift up my hand to the Lord (as the preſent General hath often done, and ſolemnly proteſted and ſworn, to make this Nation free and happy) the moſt high God, the poſſeſſor of heaven and earth, that I will not take from a thread even to a ſhoo-latchet, and that I will not take any thing that is thine, leſt thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſay, I have made <hi>Abraham</hi> rich. And honeſt and Godly (not in word and ſhew, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n real ſubſtantial actions) <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> when the cryes of the poor Jews and their wives were very great, by reaſon of the ſword and violence of their adverſaries, and the grinding oppreſſion of their Nobles and great men; Juſt <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was very angry when he heard the poor peoples cry, and rebuked the Nobles and Rulers for their oppreſſion, and ſet a great aſſembly againſt them; and ſaid unto them, It is not good that you do, ought you not to walk in the fear of our God, becauſe of the reproach of the heathen our enemies? and made them reſtore to the poor people their lands, their Vineyards, their Olive yards, and their houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they had taken by uſury, and oppreſſion from them, in the day of their ſtraites and calamity; and ſo far was
<pb facs="tcp:118510:11"/>
that juſt and righteous ſoul in the day of their Warfare, and hot conteſt with their enemies for their liberties and freedomes, from going from a poor and mean condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be worth many thouſands a year amongſt them, and to exerciſe more then princely juriſdiction and Lordſhip over them by his will and pleaſures in robbing them of all their ancient, native, fundamental rights and freedomes, that he did the quite contrary: for, ſaith he, when the time came, I was appointed to be their Governour in the land of <hi>Judah,</hi> from the 20 year to the 32 year of <hi>Artaxer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes</hi> the King; that is, twelve years I and my Brethren have not eat the bread of the Governours; but the former Governours that had been before me, were chargeable unto the people, and had taken of them bread and wine; beſides forty Shekels of Silver; yea even their ſervants bare rule over the people; but ſo did not I, becauſe of the fear of God; yea alſo I continued in the work of this Wall; neither bought we any land, and all my ſervants were gathered theither unto the Work. Moreover, there were at my Table 150 of the Jewes and Rulers; beſides thoſe that came unto us from among the heathen that are about us: yet for all this required not I the bread or the Govenour, becauſe the bondage was heavy upon the people his brethren and country-men, and therefore in the cleanneſs of his heart, and the integrity of his ſoul he cryes out, Think upon me my God for good, according to all that I have done for this people.</p>
            <p>And ſure I am that worthy man in his age, Mr. <hi>John Pym</hi> in his foreſaid excellent ſpeeches, page 22. ſaith, That ſuch Treaſons as the ſubverſion of fundamental laws, violating of liberties, can never be good or juſtifiable by any circumſtance or occaſion, and therefore by how much the more a truſt is upon a man, or generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, by ſo much the more it makes their crime in this kinde to be the more capital and haynous. Therefore to conclude, though <hi>John Lilburn</hi> the priſoner at the Bar, could and might urge many things more againſt the Parliaments legalleſt power, in all manner of ſpecial acts; or acts of Attainders, the arguments againſt which are excellently ſet down in that rational and highly to be commended plea in law, intituled The laws ſubverſion (pag. 32.) or Sir <hi>John Maynards</hi> caſe truely ſtated in 1648. by <hi>John Houlden</hi> Gentleman; and to ſay that a freeman of <hi>England</hi> by Law may be tryed by a Bill of Attainder, is irrational and unjuſt; for ſuch a proceeding is no tryal, but rather a ſentence, and it is no act of juriſdiction, but an act of the legiſlative power, but no ſentence can be paſt againſt an offender, but by ſome fore-declared viſible, known rule or law; of which the ſuppoſed offender, either actually had, or might have had knowledge. The Law ſaith, invincible ignorance of the Law excuſeth <hi>a toto</hi> from the whole offence; but ſurely then no judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be paſſed juſtly upon any man by a law that was not in being, when his ſuppoſed offence was committed in that caſe; though the fact were in it ſelf evil, yet it were not judicially evil, if no law in the Nation were extent againſt it: and ſo by conſequence a law to puniſh a perſon in that caſe, were a law to deſtroy an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent man: and whoſoever ſhall duely we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh the law-giving power, ſhall finde that the eſſential properties of that power is to reſpect things or actions that are to come, not by-paſt, and their no jurisdictions in the leaſt as to puniſh man whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that is not of them; for if my crime whatſoever, which in part is already touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon in the former part of the Priſoners Plea at the Bar, and alſo the abſolute Irrationality and Illegality, of their making a particular law, or their ſett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng up of a particular Court, for a particular man: which are notably and rationally diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon, in the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ond Edition of the book Intituled, <hi>The Picture of the Councel of State,</hi> pag. 45. and the ſecond Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of <hi>The L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gal, Fundamental Liberties of England rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, aſſerted, and vindicated,</hi> pag. 71 72, 73. For though a Parliament hath power to levie what mony they judge convenient upon the people, by a general tax for common ſafety of the Nation, which Act both by Law and reaſon they may do; yet they cannot in law equity, or reaſon lay all tax upon one, two, or three men
<pb facs="tcp:118510:12"/>
alone, and ſo make them bear all the charges of the publick, even ſo though Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may paſs Acts for the good of the People, to adminiſter law indifferently to all the people of <hi>England</hi> alike, without exception of perſons; yet they can neither by law nor reaſon, paſs a particular Act of Parliament on purpoſe to deſtroy or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn one, two, or three individual perſons, and which ſhall not in his extent or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention reach any body elſe, becauſe ſuch an Act is againſt common reaſon, common equity, all Engliſh men or people being all borne free equally alike, and the liberties and freedomes thereof being equally intailed to all alike without exception of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e in common reaſon not to be burthened with an Iron yoak of a particular Act of Parliament, when the univerſalities goeth ſcotfree in that particular</p>
            <p>Yea, he might urge many Arguments lawful to prove, that the Parliament was no Parliament: when they paſt the ſaid Act of Baniſhment, but were long before diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and that by their owne conſents, when the late Parliament took upon them the exerciſe of regality, and the diſſolution of Kingſhip, and the houſe of Lords, as it is notaly endeavoured to be proved, in the late diſcourſe of the Armies cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions: as for particularly, one licenſed to be printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and another by <hi>Richard Moon at the ſsven ſters in Pauls Church yard;</hi> and that it was long ſince diſſolved, by that learned man in the Law of <hi>England,</hi> Judge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> renders ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons in Law to prove it, as in his works printed for <hi>J. Gyles,</hi> are to be read, p. 19. 20. 26. 27. 48. 49. 50. 96. 139. 140. 142. 147. But much more full to prove its abſolute diſſolution long ſince, is Mr. <hi>Will. Prynne</hi> Barreſter at Law, In his Law-Arguments of the 16 of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. called <hi>A Legal vindication of the Liberties of England againſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal Taxes and pretended Acts of Parliament,</hi> p. 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c. and p. 44, 45, 46, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And that the Parl. Acts long ſince in Law diſſolved, the priſoner at the Bar for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plea ſaith, The death of tde King in law indiſpenſibly diſſolved the late Parl. as appears by the expreſs Judgement of the Parl. of 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>Rot. Parl. Num.</hi> 1. and the Parl. of 14 <hi>H.</hi> 4. &amp; 1 <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>Rot. Parl. N.</hi> 26. and 4 part <hi>Cooks</hi> Iaſt. <hi>f.</hi> 46. (which book was publiſhed for good Law by two ſpecial Orders of the Houſe of Commons, in <hi>an.</hi> 1641) and 4 <hi>E.</hi> 4. 44 <hi>b.</hi> For the Writ of Summons of the late Parliament, that was directed to the Sheriffs, by vertue of which men were choſen for the laſt Parl. runs in theſe words: <hi>King Charles being to have conference and treaty with and upon ſuch a day, about or concerning</hi> (as the words of the Triennial Act hath it) <hi>and high and urgent affairs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Majeſtie, the State, and the defence of the kingdom, and Church of England.</hi> But how it's poſſible for a Parl. to confer or treat with King <hi>Charles</hi> now he is dead, is not to be imagined. See 2 <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>Cook tit. Parl.</hi> 3. and therefore the whole current of the Law of <hi>England</hi> (yea Reaſon it ſelf) from the beginning to the end, is expreſly, that the Kings death doth <hi>ipſo facto</hi> diſſolve this late Parliament, though it had been all the time before never ſo entire and unqueſtionable to that very hour. And it muſt needs be ſo, he being in Law, yea and by the authority of this very Parl. ſtiled, <hi>The Head, the Beginning, and End of Parliaments.</hi> See <hi>Cooks</hi> 1 part Inſtit. <hi>f.</hi> 109. <hi>b.</hi> 110. <hi>a.</hi> and 4 part Inſt. <hi>f.</hi> 1, 2, 3. and Mr. <hi>Pym</hi>'s fore-mentioned Speech againſt <hi>Strafford, p.</hi> 8. and the Lord <hi>St. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> Argum. againſt <hi>Strafford, p.</hi> 12, 70, 71. and therefore as a Parl. in Law cannot begin without the Kings preſence in it, either by perſon, or repreſentation, <hi>Cook</hi> ibid. in part 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 6. ſee alſo <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>N.</hi> 10. ſo it is poſitively diſſolved by his death: for thereby not onely the true declared, but intended end of their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling (which was to treat and confer with King <hi>Charles</hi>) is ceaſed. See 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Cooks</hi> 7 Rep. 30, 30. and <hi>Dyer</hi> 156. &amp; 4 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>f.</hi> 43, 44. &amp; 1 <hi>E.</hi> 5. <hi>f.</hi> 1. <hi>Brooks</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, 19, 21. and thereby a final end is put unto all the means that are appointed to attain unto the end, and therefore it is as impoſſible for the late Parliament, or any Parliament ſummoned by the King, to be the Parliament in law after his death, as it is for a Parl. to make King <hi>Charles</hi> alive again. The Kings Writ that ſummoned this Parl. is the baſis in Law, and foundation of this Parl. If the foundation be deſtroyed, the Parl. falls: but the foundation of it, in every circumſtance, is deſtroyed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:118510:12"/>
the thing built upon that foundation muſt needs fall: it is a Maxime both in Law and Reaſon. But if it be objected, the law of neceſſity required the continuance of the Parliament againſt the letter of the Law. The Priſoner at the Bar anſwers; firſt, its neceſſary to conſider, whether the men that would have it continue as long as they pleaſe, or after it is in Law diſſolved, be not thoſe that have created the neceſſities on purpoſe, that by the colour thereof, they may make themſelves great and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; and if ſo, then that objection hath no weight, nor by any rules of Juſtice can they be allowed to gain this advantage by their own fault, as to make that a ground of their juſtification, which is a great part of their offence, and that it is true in it ſelf, is ſo obvious to every unbyaſſed knowing eye, it needs no illuſtration. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I anſwer, There can be no neceſſity be pretended, that can be juſtifiable for breach of truſts that are conferred on purpoſe for the redreſs of miſchiefs and grievances, yea to the ſubverſions of Laws and liberties. I am ſure Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> by the Parliaments command and order told the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> ſo, when he objected the like, and that he was the Kings Counſellor, and might not be queſtion for any thing he adviſed according to his conſcience. But ſaith Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> p. 11. he that will have the priviledges of a Counſel, muſt keep within the juſt bounds of a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, thoſe matters are the proper ſubjects of counſel, wihch in their times and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be good or beneficial to the King or Commonwealth. But ſuch Teaſons as theſe, the ſubverſion of the Laws, violation of liberties, they can never be good or juſtifiable by any circumſtances or occaſions; and therefore ſaith he, his being a Counſellor maketh his fault much more hainous, as being committed againſt a great truſt: and in page 12. he anſwers another excuſe of his which was, that what he did, he did with a good intention. Its true, ſaith Mr. <hi>Pym, Some matters that are hurtful and dangerous may he accompanied with ſuch circumſtances, as may make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear uſeful and convenient, and in all ſuch caſes good intentions will juſttifie evil counſel; but where the matters prepounded are evil in their own nature, ſuch as the matters are with which the Earl of</hi> Strafford <hi>is charged,</hi> viz. to break a publick ſaith to ſubvert laws and Government; they can never be juſtified by any intentions, how ſpecious or good ſoever they pretended; ſee in Mr. <hi>Steels</hi> anſwer to <hi>Duke Hambletons</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in the like caſe, in his caſe ſtated, pag. 12. 13. 14.</p>
            <p>The priſoner at the Bar ſhall cloſe all at preſent with this plea, <hi>viz.</hi> that although by the ſaid unjuſt Act of Baniſhment the Act it ſelf doth authorize all Judges, Maiors, Sheriffs, Bayliffs, and all other Officers, as well Military as Civil, in their reſpective places to be aiding and aſſiſting in apprehending, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſaid baniſhed Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn;</hi> yet it authorizeth none of them in the leaſt to arraign, try, condemn, and execute the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> mentioned in the ſaid Act: and therefore by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the inſufficiencie of the ſaid Act in that very particular, although <hi>John Lilburn</hi> Gent. now priſoner at the bar were that Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> mentioned in the ſaid Act of Baniſhment, (as with confidence, for the juſt and legal reaſons at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Plea mentioned, he doth a vow he is not) yet in regard the Parliament is diſſolved that made the ſaid Act, which in reaſon (by reaſon of the ſaid inſufficiency of the ſaid Act) cannot otherwiſe be ſuppoſed, but as they paſt the Act of Baniſhment themſelves againſt the <hi>John Lilburn</hi> therein mentioned and meant; ſo they reſolve to o reſerve onely to themſelves the final judging and condemning of him; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be now without their ſitting again: And that in ſpecial and extraordinary acts of Parliament (as the aforeſaid Act of Baniſhment is) there ought in law to be plain, evident, and full words, (eſpecially when it doth concern life) to demonſtrate and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs who ſhall finally put the ſaid Acts in execution. And that this is Law, the ſame Parliament that made the foreſaid Act of Baniſhment doth in ſeveral Acts ſince fully juſtifie this the priſoner at the Bar's averment of ſeveral of their Acts of Parliament, as particularly that of <hi>Aug.</hi> 2. 1650. intituled, <hi>An Act to prohibit all commerce and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique between</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>and enjoyn the departure of the Scots ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this
<pb facs="tcp:118510:13"/>
Commonwealth.</hi> In the Preamble or beginning of which, the miſchievous deſignes of the Scotiſh nation are declared, and their compelling of <hi>England</hi> to make war upon them. In the body of which Act it is declared (for the raking off, as the Act ſaith, all pretence of ignorance) and enacted, <hi>That all and every perſon or perſons within this Commonwealth</hi> (of <hi>England) or the Dominions thereof, that ſhall from and after the</hi> 5 <hi>of</hi> Auguſt 1641 <hi>uſe, hold, or maintain any correſpondency or intelligence with any perſon or perſons of the Scotiſh nation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or ſhall abet, aſſiſt, countenance, or encourage the ſaid Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh nation, or any other per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on or perſons adhering to them, in their war againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Commonwealth of</hi> England; <hi>or ſhall go o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſend, or cauſe to be ſent or conveyed any men, mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ys, horſe, arms, ammunition, or other fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niture of war, plate, goods, or merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, or other ſupply whatſoever, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o</hi> Scotland, <hi>or any ports or places thereof,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch perſon or perſons ſo offending,</hi> (without ſuch licenſe as is therein mentioned) <hi>ſhall be adjudged as Traytors to this Commonwealth, and ſhall undergo all the pains, penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and forfeitures, as in caſe of high-tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſon.</hi> And although the Scots were at preſent as great enemies to the Parliament, as the Parl. could imagine any perſons in the world could be, and the offences aforementioned of any of them againſt this nation as cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous, and the time as arbitrary a time (being a time of war) as could be imagined; yet the Parliament would be ſo juſt, even to ſtrangers and aliens, and people or a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign nation, as not to leave them arbitrary for their tranſgreſſions, to be puniſhed by whom were pleaſed firſt to lay hold of it; but in ample and plain words fixeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perſons that are to do it or execute it; therefore the Act expreſly ſaith, <hi>The ſame offences ſhall be enquired of, tryed, judged, and determined by the Commiſſioners for the high Court of Juſtice lately eſtabliſhed, in ſuch manner and form as other offences al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reſerved to the power and cognizance of that Court are to be hdard and determined.</hi> And in the ſecond part of the Act, the makers of it come to declare it treaſon for any perſon or perſons of the Scotiſh nation (without ſuch licenſe as is therein mentioned) to be found within the Lines of Communication after <hi>Aug.</hi> 10. 1631. And in the third place, the matter of the ſaid Act makes it high treaſon for any perſon or perſons of the Scotiſh nation (without licenſe as is therein mentioned) to ſtay within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of the Commonwealth after <hi>Sept.</hi> 1. 1651. Yet the priſoner at the bar, as he ſaith before, doth now avow, that the ſaid Parl. that made the ſaid Act, would be ſo juſt men unto ſtrangers and aliens, and people of a forraign nation, as not to leave them arbitrary for their tranſgreſſions, to be puniſhed by whom were pleaſed firſt to lay hold on them; but in ample and plain words fixeth upon the perſons that are to do it, or execute it: and therefore the Act again expreſly ſaith, <hi>That the ſaid offences and treaſons ſhall be proceeded againſt by the ſaid Commiſſioners of the high Court of Juſtice, who are required to give Judgement and Sentence of death againſt offenders. And every perſon and perſons ſo found guilty of the ſaid offences, ſhall ſuffer the pains of death as tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and enemies, in ſuch manner as the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall adjudge and appoint.</hi> And the ſame ample and full words as in that ſpecial Act for ſuppreſſing of Inceſt, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which by plain and evident words doth refer the puniſhment of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders therein named to the next Aſſizes or Goal-delivery to be held for the ſaid County where the fact is committed. And the very ſelf-ſame particular words are in the Act intituled <hi>An Act againſt ſeveral atheiſtical, blaſphemous, and execrable Opinions derogatory to the honour of God, and deſtructive to humane ſociety,</hi> to refer the puniſhment of all the tranſgreſſors thereof at common law before the Juſtices of Aſſize or Goal-delivery, as by the Acts themſelves doth more fully appear; unto which the priſoner at the bar for more ſafety referreth himſelf.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, the priſoner at the bar for his final plea ſaith, That Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> indicted in the ſaid Indictment now read, is none of the priſoner at the bar's name, and ſo he is not the party mentioned in the ſaid Indictment now read.</p>
            <p>All which premiſes he is ready to prove for good Law: and therefore humbly prays the judgement of the Court before he put himſelf upon any further Tryal.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 13. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Lilburn</hi> Gentleman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
